<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>OrangeShark</title><subtitle>Tag: Cinnamon</subtitle><updated>2016-07-23T14:03:02-0400</updated><link href="/feeds/tags/Cinnamon.xml" rel="self" /><link href="www.erikedrosa.com" /><entry><title>Tutorial: Hello, world! Cinnamon desklet</title><author><name>Erik Edrosa</name><email>erik.edrosa@gmail.com</email></author><updated>2014-12-31T12:00:00-0500</updated><link href="/2014/12/31/hello-world-desklet-tutorial.html" rel="alternate" /><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first of hopefully several tutorials on developing desklets for
the Cinnamon desktop environment. In this tutorial, I will cover the basics
of creating a desklet and do my best to link or refer to additional
resources where you might find more information on
the topics. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinnamon_%28software%29&quot;&gt;Cinnamon&lt;/a&gt;
is a linux desktop environment forked from Gnome Shell by
&lt;a href=&quot;http://linuxmint.com/&quot;&gt;Linux Mint&lt;/a&gt;. A desklet is a small application which
appears on the Cinnamon desktop, Cinnamon ships with three desklets and more
can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://cinnamon-spices.linuxmint.com/desklets&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Desklets
are written in JavaScript and uses CJS which is based on Gjs.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.gnome.org/Projects/Gjs&quot;&gt;Gjs&lt;/a&gt; are JavaScript bindings
for GNOME and is based on Mozilla&amp;apos;s JavaScript engine
&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Mozilla/Projects/SpiderMonkey&quot;&gt;Spidermonkey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My reason for creating this tutorial came about when I was creating a desklet
for Cinnamon. There were barely any guides or tutorials on creating a desklet
and finding documentation on the libraries available in CJS was difficult. The
only advice I saw was to read other people&amp;apos;s source code and learn from that,
while it is a great way to learn, it does not provide enough information. So
I would like to share what I have learned and where I found it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our first desklet will be a simple &amp;quot;Hello, World!&amp;quot; program, a simple program
which displays the text &amp;quot;Hello, World!&amp;quot; on the desktop using GNOME Shell&amp;apos;s
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.gnome.org/Projects/Clutter&quot;&gt;Clutter&lt;/a&gt;-based toolkit called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.gnome.org/st/stable/&quot;&gt;St (Shell Toolkit)&lt;/a&gt;. The St library
provides an easy way to create simple user interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cinnamon (I am running Linux Mint 17.1 with version 2.4.5)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Your favorite text editor&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Set up&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;apos;s start by setting up the directory for our desklet. Desklets are stored
in the user&amp;apos;s home directory ~/.local/share/cinnamon/desklets, this is where
we will work on our desklet. First, we need to create the directory of our
desklet with a unique ID or UUID in the following format &amp;quot;desklet-name@name&amp;quot;,
where desklet-name is the desklet&amp;apos;s name, in this case hello-world, and name
is either your name or your domain name. I will use the UUID
&amp;quot;hello-world@orangeshark&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-sh&quot;&gt;mkdir -p ~/.local/share/cinnamon/desklets/hello-world@orangeshark
cd ~/.local/share/cinnamon/desklets/hello-world@orangeshark&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now we need to create the structure for our project. A desklet has the
following structure:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;hello-world@orangeshark/
├── desklet.js
└── metadata.json&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The desklet.js file is where the majority of our JavaScript code will be
located. metadata.json contains, of course, the metadata for the desklet,
including the UUID and name of the desklet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;touch desklet.js metadata.json&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Time to code&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lets first define the metadata for the desklet, open up metadata.json and add
the following json.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;{
    &amp;quot;uuid&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;hello-world@orangeshark&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Hello, world! desklet&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;description&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Displays Hello, World!&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;prevent-decorations&amp;quot;: false
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The metadata contains basic information about your desklet, including the
UUID we discussed earlier. The only special property is &amp;quot;prevent-decorations&amp;quot;
which tells Cinnamon whether to apply your desktop&amp;apos;s theme or prevent it from
inheriting it. For this simple example, we will put the value false so the
desklet looks like the rest of your desktop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now for the JavaScript. There are several coding style guides to follow for
JavaScript by the GNOME project, Cinnamon seems to follow
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.gnome.org/Projects/GnomeShell/Gjs_StyleGuide&quot;&gt;this guide&lt;/a&gt;. If
you are used to using JavaScript on the web or in node.js, you might notice
a couple of differences in the language. Several of these features are
from Mozilla&amp;apos;s version of JavaScript with some being defined in future
versions of ECMAScript. I will provide links where you can find additional
information on those features as we encounter them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;const Desklet = imports.ui.desklet;

function HelloDesklet(metadata, desklet_id) {
    this._init(metadata, desklet_id);
}

HelloDesklet.prototype = {
    __proto__: Desklet.Desklet.prototype,

    _init: function(metadata, desklet_id) {
        Desklet.Desklet.prototype._init.call(this, metadata, desklet_id);
    }
}

function main(metadata, desklet_id) {
    return new HelloDesklet(metadata, desklet_id);
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The above code is all you need to create a minimal desklet. You can use it
as the basic template to start your own desklet. Now for an explanation of
each part! The first line contains const, one of those new features I
mentioned earlier, more info &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Statements/const&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
The const declaration creates a constant in the current scope, in this case
the global scope, with a value that cannot be changed through re-assignment.
We use it here to import the desklet module from Cinnamon. The next function
is our Desklet object&amp;apos;s constructor, following GNOME&amp;apos;s style guide for
creating &amp;quot;classes&amp;quot;. Using GNOME&amp;apos;s class pattern, we assign to the
prototype of HelloDesklet an object containing the methods and properties for
our HelloDesklet class. The first property &amp;quot;__proto__&amp;quot; is a special
one, it allows us to modify the prototype chain, allowing us to have a
sort of inheritance of classes. So if a property is not found in the current
instance, it will walk the prototype chain to the next prototype, in this
case Desklet&amp;apos;s prototype, and check if the property is there. So our desklet
must &amp;quot;inherit&amp;quot; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/linuxmint/Cinnamon/blob/master/js/ui/desklet.js#L35&quot;&gt;Cinnamon&amp;apos;s Desklet class&lt;/a&gt;,
Desklet contains a lot of code required by Cinnamon to set up and destroy a
desklet. The _init function is the actual constructor for our &amp;quot;class&amp;quot; and our
first task is to call the Desklet&amp;apos;s constructor, passing the current instance
using &amp;quot;this&amp;quot;. Finally the main function is the entry point to our desklet and
we just return an instance of our desklet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;const Desklet = imports.ui.desklet;
const St = imports.gi.St;

function HelloDesklet(metadata, desklet_id) {
    this._init(metadata, desklet_id);
}

HelloDesklet.prototype = {
    __proto__: Desklet.Desklet.prototype,

    _init: function(metadata, desklet_id) {
        Desklet.Desklet.prototype._init.call(this, metadata, desklet_id);

        this.setupUI();
    },

    setupUI: function() {
        // main container for the desklet
        this.window = new St.Bin();
        this.text = new St.Label();
        this.text.set_text(&amp;quot;Hello, world!&amp;quot;);
        
        this.window.add_actor(this.text);
        this.setContent(this.window);
    }
}

function main(metadata, desklet_id) {
    return new HelloDesklet(metadata, desklet_id);
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;We now import a new library, this time St or Shell Toolkit library from GNOME.
I have found &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.roojs.com/seed/gir-1.2-gtk-3.0/seed/St.html&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
documentation to be helpful in finding what classes are available in
JavaScript over the GNOME&amp;apos;s official &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.gnome.org/st/stable/&quot;&gt;C API reference&lt;/a&gt;.
Next, a new method to HelloDesklet has been added which sets up our little
window on the desktop and displays the text &amp;quot;Hello, world!&amp;quot;. We use a
StBin container that can contain a single child, which is a StLabel widget
with the text &amp;quot;Hello, world!&amp;quot;. Finally we add the label to the window with
the add_actor method and then set the desklet content with setContent method
inherited from the Desklet base class. That is it! We have finished the
basis of a simple desklet for Cinnamon. It should look something like what
you see below (the style might be different depending on your Cinnamon theme).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/imgs/helloworlddesklet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hello, World!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This concludes the tutorial for Cinnamon desklets. I plan on covering more
aspects on creating Cinnamon desklets in the future, so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>